[Music]
we should talk about that told me about
your Steve Ben and jacket my Steve ban
and jacket I stole it from my husband my
particularly is it just the kind of just
look at it this is just like the thing
that Steve baman would wear right cuz
it's militaristic or something or it's
the colour the tone the sort of slightly
army-surplus oh no you know okay partial
hipster partial army surplus I see are
trying to be like with the people kind
of thing but still being but still being
seeing the game a tough guy or something
or see if it game it's all a big game
it's all Dungeons and Dragons some kind
of you know food supply complex systems
Santa Fe Institute level yeah yeah you
just take everything to scale uh-huh oh
yeah you have to scale everything I see
yeah so that's kind of the opposite
point of view of where you come from in
a way am I getting that right or well I
mean I got us tell you that it's I think
it maybe it's a good starting place
because we're so when I say we I mean
that there's this Western cultural
history that has baked us in so deeply
into a matrix
[Music]
that it's a it's very difficult and when
I mean I'm uncomfortable saying we are
us in this because it's a different
experience for different levels at which
this current our existing system has
either benefited or betrayed but in
either department there's a bacon in
there's a baked in there's a victim a
deep you know multi decades multi
generations of brokenness mmm I was just
talking to Zach Stein and he talked
about unpadded
[Music]
do you think this event that's happening
to everybody right now is unpaid or yet
us I don't know what unpadded is I don't
know what unlearning is I feel like it's
like music okay the music is already
playing the question is what are you
gonna bring into that it's more like
alchemy as far as I can see your major
changing patterns rather than and I
think the thing to think about is you
know like an existing painting that
another another layer of paint or
landscape comes into but changes the
last one hmm
or you know when you are starting with a
soup and you have a certain set of
flavors and then you add something and
all those flavors take another direction
another they feel differently you know a
good way to look at it may because then
we're not thinking in terms of without a
continuity because there is always a
continuity isn't there between what the
past and what's happening now it didn't
just happen from nothing and we're not
just starting over or anything and
there's no way to get it out of us oh
great there's no way to get the trauma
of the last several decades out of the
vulnerable communities that have been
destroyed by it there's no way to get
the suspicions and the the the
experience of luxury and come
that has been the product of so much
exploitation out of those aspects of
those groupings of people in the culture
who have benefited from it hmm
right so it's about I mean for me this
came really clear when we were talking
about gender questions
uh-huh if only we could change this
genders behavior well hold on a second
mm-hmm
you know how do we even get how does one
begin to find the beginning in the end
of that right again that's complexity
isn't it just just because gender is is
so complex and it's not just one thing
right that's what I was wanting to ask
you about that actually that was one of
my the things I wanted to ask you about
it because I thought you might have a
nuanced answer because a lot of people
are talking about how you know they're
talking about some kind of paradigm
change and and it's it's it's it's it's
shift and gender and of some kind or and
also you're a woman and and there's a
lot more male voices out there hmm
so so yeah can you can you elaborate a
little bit can you speak a bit more
about that what what you mean by that
yeah I am I wrote this paper about it
for MIT and it's called I want you to
want me to want you and it's really
looking at sort of the trends contextual
processes there that this is cultural
this is economic this is this is this is
in the education system this is has
everything to do with intergenerational
learning this is in the media it's in
technology it's in our whole formation
of identity and it's at the level even
of physiology so when you mean it's
Jimmy in gender roles or gender
conundrum let's put it that way the
gender pain the gender brokenness the
gender possibilities hmm right all of
that stuff is
deep in the complexity of the situation
and it's just the same thinking that got
us into this mess that says what we have
to do is make the following adjustments
in this department or that department
and I guess my feeling is that you know
when I think about even like I was just
about to say it's even physiological so
you know what what turns you on like
what makes your body respond
that's ideas that's experience that's
narratives that's mythologies that's
generations of stuff there what is sexy
so it's a wild reductionism to think we
can just so that it's possible to fix
this in in one spot or another but
rather I think it's maybe a better
approach to just pause and not be
looking for a solution not be looking
for definitions of what men and women
are like strict definitions is that what
you mean and and not be looking for the
new rules of the game right so if the
rules of the seduction game are and the
seduction habits and cultures and
expectations are have led us down
because I think they've let everybody
down personally I think that men have
suffered a great deal women have
suffered a great deal people who are in
genders that are in between there or who
have you know experienced that in other
forms of their sexuality this this
modality has been painful as a painful
history in which people in all
directions have been badly hurt mm-hmm
so so what's the pain you're like
there's two things I'm getting here the
pain and then the possibility you talk
to these second possibility so so maybe
the pain is a little bit more it's more
discussed more maybe not
but but I'd also like to hear about the
possibility what you think the
possibility for let's say let's a
healthy mode of gender relations or is
that what we're talking about I I guess
for me that health is you know and I
think this actually really ties into the
whole question around paradigm shift but
it has to do with complexity and the
recognition of each person's complexity
yeah and you know I what is a healthy
sexual or or romantic or affectionate
relationship between two people well
that depends on the two people mm-hmm
and it depends on the way that they
bring out various things in each other
and how they're dealing with their
culture and how they're dealing with the
ideas that they came into and so so I
mean it kinda there are big questions in
there like is someone gonna get hurt is
there room for exploration
how much context is there is there you
know there's all sorts of stuff in there
but ultimately I think that's where the
possibility is and I would say the same
thing right now for where we are in
terms of this liminal moment between you
know pre kovat 19 and postcode with 19
then this is a moment where we go beyond
that stupid lifeboat metaphor mmm stupid
lifeboat metaphor you know the stupid
lifeboat metaphor that says well you
have to do it like this or you're gonna
break the system right I only fit 17
people on the boat and there's 32 in the
water so clearly 17 of them have to die
right which is what happens when you
think about this stuff at the wrong
level you end up with questions that
sound like that
that's called data right as opposed to
warm data like May
about warm data and yeah and the data
would be like okay which 17 people are
really good swimmers which ones have
clothes that are extra that can be tied
together to help pull people in the
water who lose but knowledge of you know
where we're going who's got right so
there's all kinds of questions that have
to do with the complexity of each of the
17 persons mm-hmm that's may not even
say people let's say persons mm-hmm
because this person is a unique costume
yeah and and those are like just
possible possibility vectors where
possibility vectors so that's I think
where I'm going with all of this is into
those those details and kind of out of
the the sweeping calculations mm-hmm
okay yeah because what about like
primordial let's say I know we have a
probably stereotypical idea of that
primordial roles because I think that
for example I think that you know we had
a very polarized view of male and female
you know in in an industrial society you
know and then we move into
post-modernism which just flattens
everything and then there's no
definition there's no contour there's no
we're just all the same and then we're
moving out into some other thing where
we want to have a more complex idea of
what male and female is perhaps but we
also want to recover let's say some of
the primordial qualities of that would
you agree with what I'm saying or I
actually don't know what to do with that
because my experience says this I wake
up in the morning with my partner and we
try to figure out how to get through the
day as best we can mm-hmm right and that
means that in every aspect of the day in
some way or another we are having to go
beyond roles beyond the roles the
culture has to
beyond the rules some of the biology has
has maybe produced so we what are we
doing we're in the culture that's
completely dysfunctional that's premise
on exploitation and extraction and it's
filled with all kinds of messaging that
leads to messaging that leads to
messaging around like I was saying even
our identities what is a what is a
success what does it mean to be a
success mm-hmm what does it mean to be
sexy what does it mean to be kind what
does it mean to be important so all of
those questions come into what these
roles and these assumptions and even our
physiological responses to what is
attractive right and so but they're
theirs they've been cooking in the soup
of a really screwed up culture yeah stew
for a long time and so I'm really
hesitant to lean back into that because
I in my experience who it's possible for
me to be changes depending on who I'm
with sure it's a relational process and
so the more attentive I am to those
relational processes the more
possibility I have to perceive instead
of thinking oh well this is just how it
is right and I am very leery of notions
of human nature because those notions
are produced by humans and so there's a
there's a trap there's a trap there hmm
so let's say I was I was I was watching
your film about about your father and
and he went to study
I guess in Polynesia I can't remember
the the names of the tribes with with
Margaret Mead and why when you were
talking I was just thinking about that
and I was thinking about how they saw
like how they saw what a human being is
and its role and that kind of thing like
compared to how we see it and and how
radically different those two views of
the world are well I think what you're
you're poking at here is kind of the
essence of why this is an important
conversation to have now because I guess
what happens in that cultural confusion
or the cultural curiosity or noticing
that other there are other possibilities
than the ones that have been so
entrenched and just woven in every
nuance of our language of it you know
all of these these deep ideas they form
a kind of matrix inside of which it
becomes impossible to create change
because the change is informed by the
matrix that that you're trying to change
and so you end up in this question of
how do we change the system when we are
the system and we're inside the system
and yeah and and you know if three weeks
ago they were all these issues that were
absolutely impossible to imagine mmm
stopping the airplanes what yeah
people home with their kids actually
everybody became a home school that's a
shock to me and that's that's it that's
been an incredible for me personally
that that's that's been an eye-opener
it's like I've always thought that I'd
rather homeschool my kids if I had the
possibility but now I know that that's
true you know right I'm not saying that
I think that it should be like that for
everybody but
and and now we don't know that should
you know that should just cut brackets
on it and that should didn't have
brackets on it didn't have quotation
marks on it it wasn't in question yeah
week six weeks ago so that's a big shift
huge and we where its radical and so
it's much more radical than the being
hung with your kids
it's the idea yeah yeah you're talking
about possibility and that's what we're
talking about this I think this shows
even though it's just you know it has
this terrible other side to it this
event shows certain possibilities I
don't know if these possibilities will
be manifested and I tend to be kind of
cynical about whether they will be or
not but even the idea of them being
there being a possibility seems to be
extraordinary
yeah it is extraordinary and I think
when you were talking about Gregory and
Margaret in New Guinea and Bali it's um
I think what's important about that
experience that Gregory was describing
there I'm gonna lean more onto his his
version of that is the way that it
brought questioning to his own
epistemological assumptions mmm-hmm
right so right it's not so much about
forming descriptions of other cultures
as it is about recognizing that there
were limits on your own hmm and and
before one has access to really
perceiving of their possibilities and
ways of being it can appear that
marriage is marriage and money is money
and time is time and you know age is age
and woman is woman and man is man and
that these things are are is is and then
when you start to perceive things in
another culture you realize oh my is is
different than there is so what it is
in the word something what is this what
is this and and that's an important
question that's the moment I think that
gives us that liminal pause of
possibility
yeah I remember he's saying and saying
in the film that you think your five
fingers are fine fingers but it's
actually the relationship between the
fingers which is what way more complex
then let's say or an image in the mind
of what fingers are and I guess I guess
if we're asleep we tend to think and
sort of fixed images of things and the
more we wake up we tend to the more we
see the living reality we tend to those
those images kind of dissolve does that
does that make sense and we we just stop
seeing the world as in terms of things
and objects and and I think that's what
you're that's what your whole thing is
isn't it about relationships seeing the
world those relationships am I getting
that right yeah I mean the beauty of
relationships is they're not fixed
mm-hmm right so if we see the world in
terms of relationships there's a lot
more possibility for perceiving
possibility as opposed to if you
perceive things and if gender is a thing
or culture is a thing or an economy as a
thing or an I identity is the thing
instead of looking at each of those as
nests of relational process all of which
are changing all the time
mm-hmm they're not things there are no
things there's no thing right right so
so you know identity what is identity
right identity is actually all
relational mm-hmm so it's you know your
relationship to the economy your
relationship to the culture your
relationship to your body your
relationship to your former generations
your relationship to the future
generations your relationship to ideas
your relationship to music your
relationship to your sexuality whatever
but it's all relational and when those
relationships start changing there's a
question Oh Who am I mm-hmm right that's
the question that's getting poked right
now that
scaring a lot of exactly exactly because
we are forced into looking into that
question whether we like it or not it's
almost like the big spiritual question
has arrived you know it's it's it's
arrived in a mass or something and it
arrived from multiple contexts right
it's not at one context all of a sudden
it's it's who are you as a dad because
you've got your kid in your face who are
you in relationship to all this
technology who are you economically
who are you culturally who are you in
your body at your health in your body in
your age like you know suddenly I am
realizing that you know you and I we
have some gray hair yeah yeah we are
actually in the safe zone anymore
yeah and that's you know that's a
question whoo-hoo Who am I who are you
in in post coded world well you're
you're more vulnerable that's that's for
sure I mean we're we're we're vulnerable
I guess especially if we have gray hair
or and you know there's a there's a lot
of people who have been so vulnerable to
begin with you are even more vulnerable
right right and so that but again it's
also I'm sorry to interrupt I also think
with the vulnerability there comes the
possibility to observe another kind of
strength in you at the same time so it's
again this double-edged yeah I mean I
think the lack of vulnerability is a
weakness for sure you know the people
who are running around feeling
invincible right now they're not only
their own weakness but they're a
weakness to the whole community they're
showing the weakness of the media the
weakness of science the weakness of
economy the weak they are like walking
around being the epitome 'he's the
weakest part of our culture because
they're creating weak links with all the
ideas
that gave them that invincible idea
mm-hmm I am invincible
I'm not worried I'm not afraid I'm not
gonna get sick and die from this and it
said well what you have just exposed is
actually that you don't see but your
health is not your own mm-hmm that's
profound - yeah that's if people could
understand that perhaps that would be
profound if I could understand that I
should say people and some preachy kind
of way of it so because I guess the ego
feels and you know thinks it's
invincible and yet we have we have this
part of us since on some level that is
like oh yeah you know it feels it feels
above the the above nature above reality
it seems to be a big a big theme it's an
important theme of being a human being
in this era where climate crisis is
looming where there's all these you know
obviously the economic global economic
system is not cannot be run with the
level of exploitation and extraction it
has the education system is you know
developed to produce this eco economic
system the cultures right the whole
thing is running on this invincible drug
and it just seems to me that this
question of actually being being
vulnerable
I don't just mean emotionally vulnerable
I mean physically vulnerable is you know
like we could be some of the last
generations of this version of Homo
sapiens mm-hmm right so this this is a
deep shift of of humility that that one
of the greatest strengths right now is
the capacity to learn the capacity to
see outside your matrix the capacity to
question the capacity need to pause mm
hmm hmm the capacity need to to look for
the complexity of the persons of the
moment instead of looking for a map or a
strategy mmm yeah yeah yeah I mean it's
definitely uh all those things you're
talking about I feel somehow when this
happened I feel like I all these things
you're talking about I had at least some
understanding of them on a theoretical
level you know but when you say it now
it's it's something different than if
you had said those things
a month ago I might have been thinking
it on a more intellectual level or
something right it's not an abstraction
anymore it's it's no longer an
abstraction but not that's that that's I
think that's an extraordinary kind of
experience that maybe people are having
it's just the real is approaching on the
realist is is more as more vivid yeah
and it's the blurring is more vivid
right so the the blurring of how can a
health issue be an economic issue being
an education issue be a culture issue
via science issue be irate it's all one
issue so there's there no way to pull
this thing into pieces and fix it
it's various roles right there's that
roles you can't you can't divide this
thing back into sectors and fix it
mm-hmm
it doesn't look that it's not possible
it's not living there mm-hmm it isn't
the sector's it's this connective tissue
between them and so there's actually
nobody positioned to respond
there's nobody no person position to
respond there's no Ministry of the
liminal you know like that make sure
there's nobody whose job it is to tackle
all this at once and so you have oh
there's no ministry but then there's the
spontaneous response that is happening
right because anyways right right
because we are actually living beings
and we're not we're not um totally numb
we might be a little numb but we're not
totally them so there's a need to to
respond from a different positioning
it's I'm fascinated by the way in which
there's some these big questions even
about you know what how how science
works in this mm-hmm oh yeah this is
good because one of the questions I
wanted to ask you actually and from
watching your film about your father and
thinking about your childhood and the
thinking about the fact that you were
raised and I remember him saying in the
film that the arts came came before
science for him on some level like the
ground was kind of the arts and that not
moved into science I'm not sure if I'm
getting that that right or that's what
he wanted to say but I kind of wanted to
talk to you about that the relationship
between the arts and science or a
relationship between let's say a
scientific response we could talk we
could talk about the response to what's
going on today or and let's say a poetic
or
artistic response and I know that I know
that your father sort of almost he saw a
science and in a very poetic way or or
something like that yeah this is a
really big deep convoluted question yeah
yeah I I think let's go back to this
notion of the matrix okay and let's talk
about how what where where it's possible
to to learn because you know it's it's
really all too easy to find what you're
looking for and the the the issue around
what keeps happening with trying to get
out of the matrix is that the plans to
get out of the matrix are informed by
the matrix and so it ends up not getting
us out yeah but instead getting us
deeper in because the actual thinking
patterns are what has produced the set
of traps you know Wittgenstein talked
about this the fly in the bottle you
know and the fly can't see that it's in
a bottle and because it banging its head
against it just yeah it has no idea that
it's in a bottle so and that's a little
bit of where we are and until you get
these cracks until you get these broken
pieces or you see something that is not
of your culture is not of its its
business that's breaking those patterns
or creating a disruption in them it's
very difficult to notice that they're
even there hmm you know like if you're
in water that's that's body temperature
you could just not even feel that water
and so that's that's kind of what we
have been in is and we being well we've
had too much familiarity comfort mmm and
sleepiness or something like that well
some people have and some people haven't
Yeah right well that's you know the the
the fallacy of the success of the
existing system is only harbored by the
people who have comfortable living rooms
yeah right so let's don't forget that
you know certainly in my work when I'm
working in vulnerable communities and
places where there's been a huge
betrayal by the system those groupings
of people are the fastest to see the
systemic issues because they live in
them hmm right there's no room to have
the idea that this is the successful
system this is not a successful system
mm-hmm unless you happen to be you know
sitting comfortably in the exploits of
it so so yeah so what what do we do what
is this biz what is information how do
we if we got new information would we
even be able to see it mm-hmm what kind
of question can we not ask because we've
never thought of asking it because it's
outside the peripheries of the patterns
of thinking that that are familiar
mm-hmm
so this these are the kinds of questions
that when we're trying to think about
what does it take to have what is the
relationship between art and science
so the the arts actually provoke the
possibility for perception to take place
because they provide an irrational world
hmm and that irrational Ness is really
really necessary it's that that that
thing you know that allows stuff breaks
the matrix it breaks out of the box it
if if it's possible to perceive it but
but there's also the possibility of
using those same metaphors to generate
our
and to pull on I'm wearing my Steve
Bannon jacket today and to pull on those
those fears and unspoken qualities that
can actually drive us deeper in so we
have every every capacity as human
beings to think what we want is systems
change start to feel the passion and the
fervor of wanting to create that
system's change and create a change that
gets us deeper in to where we were
hoping to get out of yeah yeah I see
that I see that a lot I think that's
happening a lot you know I think the
almost the fury that people have just
entrenches them deeper into the system
they become pawns for you know the
people that are that are keeping them in
that system or yeah and and they nothing
I mean I've done it yeah okay it's like
so seductive that it's you the problem
is you don't know when you're doing it
because it's it's that glass jar that
you're in with us that's why you just
you you know it's it's what that danger
is right there so I guess you know one
thing about this moment right now is
that since everything's different
yeah it's a good time to kick some
addictions
you know we you've never been a smoker
or had any kind of addictive mm-hm
stuff in your life when you're in a
moment where all the patterns change
that's a really good time to kick yeah
sure but there's there's a kind of cold
turkey going on yeah yeah bringing it
back back to the Arts and the
possibility of let's say of poetry it
occurs to me when you were talking that
that's the thing that the arts in the
poetry can do is provide that depth to
to ideas right you know because if we
just have an idea we tend to run with
and become very ideologically possessed
on some level but if we have if we have
a deep if there's a deep complex poetic
sense of our experience then then we're
not so easily you know fooled by
bye-bye easy bye-bye ready-made
or easy patterns it's a tricky one
because I think you can also look at
some of the darkest moments in human
history and see how they were actually
fueled by metaphor and the arts mm-hmm
so it can cut either way okay and but
there is there is a loosening okay so
once it but the question is once it's
loose then what so art the arts might
have a quality of loosening up the fixed
patterns and then the patterns could go
into something extreme again or
something like this they could lock get
locked in or something more living could
be creative yeah and and where does that
set of pathways come from I have no idea
I mean where do where does that happen
where does it happen where does it
happen that you know using that metaphor
of addiction that that sometimes when
people have addiction they destroy their
family they abandon their elders they
abandon their kids and then one day
something else comes along that might
first be perceived as somewhat
inconsequential but it's the thing that
actually allows the learning to take
place and there's the turnaround yeah
other people never get there and they
just go all the way down and they don't
they don't get they don't get out so a
you know there's some and this is where
I think we're it's the trans contextual
learning thing is really important is
that there's um trans can sexual yeah
our multidisciplinary or just knowing a
lot of different fields rather than
being ghettoized in one
well like when we were talking about
identity mm-hmm what context is your
identity in you know it's multiple
context what disciplines how about the
disciplines I mean I I think it's more
contextual than disciplinary so you know
I agree with that yeah so my identity if
there's a change in my identity that
change is going to be produced and and
reflected and engaged across multiple
and through multiple contexts right so
here I am I'm stuck at home yeah there's
a change and that change is in my
relationship with my partner it's in my
relationship with my even my wardrobe my
pajamas all the time yeah just the top
everybody's in their sweatpants and so
but but also what I'm eating what I'm
thinking about what I'm reading what
kind of conversations I'm having you
know I don't spend any of that time when
I used to spend plotting and planning
schedules yeah whole conversation is
gone I'm not spending any time booking
airplane tickets I'm not spending any
time producing powerpoints for key notes
yeah I'm not spending you know like my
losses liberation of time hmm so all
these different contexts are changing in
the same time but they have different
time qualities to them so it's it's this
is what I mean about trends contextual
shift if I had said to myself in
February or late January what I need is
to make some changes in my life I like
the picked a few categories to change
yeah I need to get more exercise I need
to change my diet I need to have some
more
time with my partner hmm right and they
would have been those are like
reductionist approaches to solutionizing
the need for change I've identified that
something needs to change
yeah but you see the difference so you
try to change them in categories instead
of instead of finding out how would you
change I mean how do we change well as
you say you see that's kind of
mysterious how the you know the
alcoholic would decide one day that you
know you suddenly have a turn around and
but something comes in hitting bottom
side right something came in the virus
was a systems change bringer a prett
right it brought it we've been talking
you know change agents um change makers
and all this blah blah blah yeah no one
was making any change at all yeah
exactly yeah so then along comes a
little itty-bitty virus and now we're
changing so but but the thing is this
it wasn't trying to change one thing at
a time it came in as a trans contextual
systems changer everything changed
mmm-hmm and that's how systems change
happens
that's how system change happens hmm but
we can't really create let's say a
positive virus like how would we how
would we create like a good virus I mean
good and bad again and again good and
bad it's it's kind of ridiculous isn't
it but what is positive systems change
no how would you know like how how bad
do we have if it's the socio-economic
response technological response to this
is to create higher levels of
surveillance and police state and
control and all of these dark things
they do contribute looming right now
mm-hmm
if that's the response then my guess is
there's a bigger crash coming after that
yeah sure yeah right so what's it gonna
take to learn how to actually live in a
way that produces vitality in life
sure yeah and and so where it seems if
in getting in touch with suffering on
some level right I mean I just think of
the Buddhists first noble truth that's
the beginning right so I was thinking
what could a positive virus be but but
no it's not that it's that it's that we
have to get in touch with our suffering
and on some level maybe or there has to
be a shift in perception of what it is
that is is what what are we learning
what are we learning right so it's it's
kind of an evolutionary question mm-hmm
and so if there is the possibility of
learning now that we you know that that
economies that are based on built-in
obsolescence and exploitation and
extraction don't actually produce life
then we have a different problem to work
on which is how then do we find a way to
produce a decent way of being alive for
seven billion people yeah right and
that's a different set of questions then
how do we go back to the normal we had
which was actually which was actually
creating all kinds of problems not just
viruses but over behind their problem so
so is the what but you never know and I
don't think it's for anyone to judge is
this what is a good systems change and
what is a bad systems change it is for
us to not be numb right and I get really
itchy about the kind of discussion
around what are the opportunities that
are arising out of you know because to
me that is a red flag that that this
kind of attraction to ever positive
thinking could easily prohibit the pain
and the sensation of well that's why
what I was trying to get I was suffering
because because because I thought so
yeah
yeah yeah we have to be able to feel the
rate which feel the pain feels a little
feel the back feel the crack in our
matrix mm-hmm it's never going to be
easy of course not
yeah that makes sense
mm-hmm but the sensitivity to it is I
think the development well I was
thinking that there's something about
the capitalist system right is that
human beings it works B it works and it
destroys at the same time because we
like excess right we just we just want
to create more and more and more and
more and we just keep going and we don't
again we don't really stop but there's
there's this constant excess which is
why it does the opposite doesn't work
when you try to control everything and
you try to you know you try you try to
have a communist country and you try to
manipulate everything so that everybody
is the same so both of those kind of
extremes I was thinking what do we do
with the excess right of human you know
folly right you know William Blake says
if a fool persist in the folly they
become wise I'm wondering if that's like
this persistent folly that the culture
has been engaged in for so long has a
possibility at least a few people you
know will become more wise and that that
might be good it also has the
possibility that a few people will go
crazy and it's a tricky one because
sometimes fear and pain make produce
contraction right and sometimes fear and
pain produce learning and it's you don't
get to say when and where which happens
you know so there's there's I don't know
what to say about that it's just it's
like it's a roll of the dice and
[Music]
yeah well I feel like whenever I what
you're always trying to make me do is I
I'm trying to look for a solution for
something and you and you keep saying hi
wait a minute like things are more
complex than that I have to sort of
temper my my my you know like you could
have a silly pessimism which I mean a
sort of nihilistic pessimism or you
could have a ridiculous optimism you
have to kind of steer your boat in the
middle and in a way you don't want to
fall into this nihilistic dislike of the
human experience or or or just become
more optimistic when when we're in the
face of so much you know you know
darkness all around and so I as far as I
can see it's double binds and paradoxes
all the way down all the double-blind -
yeah and so I think that the reason that
I keep doing this to you and I'm
apologize but I do do this to people but
but it's that there it's not about
finding solutions it's about standing in
the tension it's about being in and and
attention right well that's that's the
thing in your film I I was struck by you
saying cuz usually we talk all the
double bind yeah I get that that's a
problem that's how I always thought of
the double bind and you say no the
double bind is the opportunity when
you're when you can see the double bond
that's the dialectic then it's it's a
it's a it's a creative imperative it's
That moment when rate of imperative yeah
then there has to be another a whole
another whole perception of this thing
that seemed like an impossible set of
circumstances and and that's that's what
I mean about the the lifeboat metaphor
right if you look at the lifeboat
metaphor as there's 32 people in the
water and 17 on the boat and that boat
can only take 17
so you have to figure out who's gonna
die right it's the wrong question it's a
horrible thing isn't it to write
somebody yeah but but I'm just using
that because it's the kind of question
that people keep presenting and it's the
wrong kind of question it's it's it's
like informed by the kind of thinking
that is thinking about you know how many
boards does it take to build something
or how many parts are in the engine and
if you don't have enough parts you don't
have an engine if you have too many
parts you have leftovers you don't put
extra parts in an engine just to put
extra parts in but you can put extra
people in a boat you can divide the
weight in different ways you can figure
out who swims you can respond so it's
it's like when you're asking questions
and forming inquiry about living systems
the whole thing changes yeah and and
there are these tensions and these
paradoxes these double clients that move
in in entirely different ways than if we
were trying to you know solve for X and
and so I think that's that's where I I'm
always trying to hold the door open
don't be in a hurry to solve this just
be in it because your attention in in a
paradox or in a double-blind when you're
paying attention what you get is it is
the benefit of zoom in zoom out
simultaneously uh-huh and in that you
will be able to see potentialities and
possibilities that you didn't otherwise
have access to
uh-huh right right if you just zoom out
you miss all the detail if you just zoom
in you miss all the context mm-hmm but
together but that's a kind of it's a
kind of exercise a kind of muscle a kind
of
well that that goes back I think to arts
and the poetics because you can't write
a poem I mean or write a song or you
don't say okay I'm gonna write a song
now like you can't just construct some
something like that right you have to
you have to you have to kind of you have
to be in a moment you have to allow the
moment to emerge or something in you and
then and then and then so you're zooming
out and looking at it and you're
assembling things but the same time
you're being taken over by something
else does that make sense oh so much
sense yeah yeah I mean I feel that all
the time even when when I watched that
film that you're referring to that I
made I can't tell you how many times
I've watched it and I thought wow I
wonder how I ever came up with the idea
to have put those two shots together
what a great idea that was that was a
really good idea how did I get come up
with that and it's like this bizarre
kind of there's no authorship there no
there's no no I agree
whatever the hell that the whole concept
is it's wrong it had to do with some I
mean I didn't even see some of the the
things that I did that were the best
parts of that film until years later
yeah well I was talking to John for
Vicki he talks about dialogue OC about
this kind of sacred dialogue and he says
when you're really in dialogue goes then
this third factor emerges so and he
called it the third factor this third
sort of thing in that and not that you
know again you can't even put a name to
that that it's it is but it's definitely
not you don't create it with any kind of
intentionality I don't think I think it
just overtakes you in some way on the
contrary I think if you try to put
intentionality on it it runs away
exactly yeah it's it doesn't it doesn't
like it on the other hand you have to do
the work and you have to you know invite
it like you can't just write gotta have
this skill you gotta have worked for it
you gotta practice you got to make the
I'm for it and then you have to not be
let it fall apart or something you have
to let things fall apart this way yeah
get out of the way
hmm yeah I don't know it's a funny thing
it's a funny thing but I am I don't know
I don't know what do you think where are
we what happens now and we're you know I
think this is a critical moment of the
the vortex the you know post normalcy
are like yeah well I mean you know the
word that comes to me is like
groundlessness and but groundlessness is
sort of possibility so I feel like I
don't know I can't speak for other
people's lives but I feel like there's
it's a weird it's a weird thing it's
like it's like something is opening up
and saying okay this is how this is here
here's what could happen and here's what
potentialities are there and and in a
few months it's just gonna close down
again on some level and then at that
point we're going to have to keep
whatever we've learned in this sort of
you know and from this situation and and
that will be like this is like a retreat
or something you know I've done Buddhist
meditation for a long time it's a bit
like that you go into you go in you go
out into a place you go out you go away
from the world for a while and and then
you come back changed even though things
are the same and when you go back
everything's a shock and everything's
kind of hard to to navigate and then you
realize maybe a few years later that
that that you've maybe learn something
yeah I keep feeling that that it's one
of those moments that maybe is something
like when you're on a boat and you're
leaving and headed out to sea and you
can still see the land
I think right now we can still see the
land Oh
maybe yeah that's the other thing as
maybe things are just gonna get really
weird just just completely weird maybe
things are just gonna go so I you know
anything's possible right now we could
go back to the land we could go out to
sea we could find a new island we could
good you know we could with anything's
possible
and but I think it has to do with the
details right back to the yeah back to
the relationship between complexity and
details so you know what are the ways in
which scientific research is actually
being strangled by culture that's a big
question can you elaborate I'm not sure
if I understand what you mean by that
well okay it's a it's a complex question
because there's a of course right now
we're in this moment and hopefully we'll
look back on this tape and say remember
how stupid we all were we're really
people don't can't really get medical
attention until they're in critical
condition yeah okay the the basic
approach at this point is still the
ventilators there's not enough
billionaires are going out buying their
own ventilator good for them yeah well
at least someone will be safe but the
ventilator is not a solution I don't
know if you know anybody who's come out
of intubation but I heard some horror
stories not pretty and it's years of you
know rehabilitation coming
so clearly the ventilator cannot be the
solution and there's you know what what
about early treatment what about you
know what what is is are there are there
in the immunities or are there not this
is an unknown question how but we're
also in
in a culture and in a in a moment where
the economics and the cultural and the
media and all of these things have
formed this kind of perfect storm yeah
nobody believes anything that comes from
anywhere anymore right we don't believe
the pharmaceutical companies because we
know they lie we don't believe the the
New Agers and the alternative medicines
because they've been lying we don't
believe the politicians because they'll
say anything just everybody's been lying
yeah yeah yeah so actually how do we
retrieve how is it possible to retrieve
the integrity of scientific research in
the field because there's no time for
years and years of clinical studies to
so how what what on this in this moment
what would make you trust or feel that
it was feasible to get behind well I
mean it's a question of also of personal
responsibility as well as like taking
care of your your health because if
you're just eating a lot of bad food and
and you know you know overworking
yourself and being burnt out and your
immune system is going to be weak and
you know we're you know this is all sort
of I don't know though because you know
there's a lot of people who are that are
people that I know that have been really
healthy sure yeah okay I see what you
mean yeah that's taking I'm taking out
of just a personal tragedy element of
the thing but I'm saying again it's it's
a question of looking at the system and
seeing how the systems are are bad like
that the health system you know and
bringing it to a more local kind of
understanding I mean the health system
has created a completely reductionist
idea of health yeah exactly right
so that is a deeply decades built-in
disaster so you know this your lung
health is separate from your eye health
is separate from your I mean dentistry
is not even part of the doctor's office
and clearly my teeth are part of my body
so you know there's this this kind of
separation that's been developed in the
health sciences and then you add that to
the kind of reductionism that has taken
place in the marketplace around what it
is to have a viable medicine for sale
and what it is that how that then got
ported into the research facilities and
the universities and the universities
are really only able to look at one
context or one discipline at a time so
they couldn't get the trans contextual
information if they wanted to and so you
know meanwhile all of this has been
building for years and in and that's
part of why I think there is so much
distrust in in the media in the
journalism in the information because
it's it doesn't have the context it
doesn't have you know the question is
not is this a proven solution the
question is who paid for the research
mm-hmm
where was it done what questions did
they ask how much contact was there they
had an agenda
yeah and how much money are they earning
how much money you know from from
selling ritalin to to children or
whatever or whatever so this is I think
the the kind of the puzzle of this
moment is we're back to the question at
the beginning what what is information
Rebecca complexity again huh yeah how do
we know what information is in a coma
system hmm because it's a slippery
question right right and often we think
of information in terms of you know in a
very new Merkle as you say cold data and
warm data
we look at the cold data or we're not
even I don't think said it would be
possible from looking at your let's say
we were gonna do an analysis of you
mm-hmm
and let's say six weeks ago we looked at
your economic your microbiome your I
don't know your time spent at home your
your age your blood your heritage your
DNA your culture how much you read what
degrees you have what other things
you've said what would we have known
from looking at all of that nothing
about how you would be changing and
learning in this moment yeah virtually
nothing nothing yeah yeah yeah that's my
point
yeah so and and so yeah it's a trick
this is a really tricky moment because
the question of how to actually bring
integrity to this this set of questions
that face us of how to treat each other
how to treat this virus how to treat the
notion of what is a livelihood what does
it mean to yeah what I keep what's
always so surprising is just how how
many areas of life this whole thing is
touching or you just mentioned
livelihood talking about medicine we
talked about education we talked about
you know just whatever you know every
aspect of our life is being affected by
this tiny little virus so it's not even
the virus at all it's actually
everything else as well yeah and it's it
was there I mean not all of these issues
were there there's been people pointing
to him for decades centuries actually
mm-hmm and
[Music]
so we get it we get an opportunity
there's that opportunity world yeah
you've said opportunity a lot but you've
also said that you don't like the idea
of thinking too much in opportunistic
terms right I don't like the kind of
flat and sterile Victor's of vision that
the notion of opportunity can create
right if I say what's the opportunity
and we'd say we could learn to think in
terms of inter dependency that becomes
an abstraction comes blah blah yes sure
great so that's where I feel like it's
important to watch out and that's where
the arts okay back to the arts so
occasionally you get these fantastic
sci-fi writers who can really bring
detail into those casting visions into
the future mm-hmm a lot of them are very
very dystopian but but it's those
details that most of the visioning lack
[Music]
right so that's why opportunity can be a
really it's a to say that can be an
invitation to some really bad thinking
mm-hmm incomplete a lot of
incompleteness there well I guess what
you were saying about the science
fiction writers is is that you know
they're able to take this intuitive leap
probably right that if you're just
thinking in empirical terms or
scientific terms you might get stuck in
the you might get stuck in and you might
get a combinatorial explosion you have
too many options and too many ideas and
too much abstraction and but but it's
just the the imaginative leap or
something it that's what that's what
creative people can can do or that's
maybe maybe that's what education should
be that's what we should be trying to
teach people on some level is is to
combine like let's say as you say that
the details and the context and being
able to take an imaginative leap
the richness that multi-sensorial
attention mm-hmm right right so that's
why you know that one of the problems
with opportunity is that it it brings a
kind of flat positivity with it it
brings an instrumentalization or
something or a very left brain kind of
like you know it doesn't trying to get
something out of it or yeah link to to
reductively here or just not wanting to
feel the pain again you know if you if
you're but we have to focus on the
opportunities we have to think what
could what we could possibly do with
this experience yeah you know and at the
same time it's like yeah and I actually
need to feel the fury and the grief at
the same time of you know people who's
who are having to be on the other side
of decision-making that says you're your
person is not getting care this other
person is getting care mm-hmm yeah
that's a whole mass that if I just turn
my back on that and think I'm just gonna
think about the positive side of this
bill is terrible painful then there's a
numbness that is not able to inform in
the way that that sci-fi artistry and
imagination needs to have that
multi-sensorial mm-hmm formation and I
also integration of the darker side of
how you know what when you were saying
that I was thinking like you think of
somebody making these kind of decisions
which affect people's lives in a
Cavalier kind of way and I was thinking
you would feel if that if you were in
that situation you would feel murderous
right
I mean when you don't know the rage you
want would want to feel you would want
to you know if somebody was doing that
to somebody you love you could easily
feel violence to a lot of violence you
know inside yourself and I think we want
to live in this safe abstraction all the
time and not realize that we have those
deeper darker kind of you know feelings
you know what it is andrew is that
there's I think it's a really pernicious
habit there's this utilities ation of
emotion and people will say there's no
point in getting angry about this
because there's nothing you can do about
it oh yeah yeah okay there's no point in
being frustrated that you don't know or
that you're afraid because there's no
way to know its own anything yeah nurten
t all right and to this I just want to
say you yeah because you're talking
it sounds like you're you're you're
speaking to children when you talk to
somebody like that isn't it it's it's a
it's a benevolent sort of it's it's like
saying turn off half your your your
nervous system it's like it's an
anesthetize a ssin yeah at the very
moment when we're walking on slippery
rocks and you need to be able to feel
with your bare feet every piece of algae
that you step on right you need to be
able to feel that in order to know where
to go and this this anesthetize ation is
a disaster mm-hmm but to feel it is
attention its rigor it's hard work yeah
it's it's not gonna relent on you and if
you 12 too much in the negative and the
the you know and the the dystopian
version you're not going to be able to
perceive the possibilities perceive stay
in the possibilities and you can't
perceive the risks sure right so so so
you either you're either just utopian or
just
you're projecting some future that you
and but not being in relation to the
present or your your you're dwelling in
how dark you know everything can be or
and you're not seeing that as you say
they're the richness of you know even
though of both like the fact that there
were life and death are kind of
happening simultaneously around you
there's this possibility and also also
some when there's one possibility arises
another thing disappears and in the
meantime you have to keep asking the
question Who am I mm-hmm
right and so the this whole utilitarian
version of what emotions you're allowing
to guide you or inform you is a disaster
because in the mean time you need to
keep thinking who am i right that those
nurses that are in that predicament are
asking hard questions Who am I mm-hmm
and if you can't ask that question
because you can't feel the pain or
you've shut out the possibility of that
developmental process because it was too
stretchy it was too painful then were in
trouble so my question then is how do we
support each other through this process
in a way that doesn't dull our senses
and it's it's the I have a little puppy
yeah I just got this little puppy which
is why I missed our thing yesterday
because I completely got puppy brain and
lost my mind but my puppy was out
yesterday and just eating all sorts of
dirt and rocks and grass and no doing
research right and then vomiting
rocks and grass all over my kitchen
floor yeah in the city they would eat
chewing gum and cigarette butts and
practically everything that
as on the sidewalk right yeah no if I
don't allow my puppy to eat dirt and
rocks and grass hmm there's some you
won't puke on my floor mm-hmm it will
have been very efficient but there won't
be the knowing right and so I you know
the it's it's it's a big it's a big it's
a big question and particularly when
we're adding this to societies of people
who are already dealing with levels of
depression and brokenness and anxiety
and and then we throw this in as a as a
as a crack in the matrix glass mm-hmm
and and anyone well I guess Geiger Jeff
said there's conscious suffering and
then there's just unconscious suffering
so well it's been forced upon us so you
know it happened and it it's gonna
continue to happen probably for a while
because the fallout from the various
things that have changed will continue
though I'm quite sure technologically
economically and how many people's I
heard a story last night of this this
one couple who two hours before the
lockdown the the one partner said to the
other one I want a divorce and hours
later they went into lockdown together
and they've been in lockdown for three
weeks stuck in the same house and yeah
did they work it out or did they decide
they still wanted a divorce her I don't
know yet but there's other people who
may have been thinking about it who then
find each other again
or people who thought they had a happy
marriage and then they were
actually this was really working great
when I didn't have to spend any time
with you yeah so and there's a of course
an enormous spike of domestic abuse yeah
god no it's just it's just anything it's
it's everywhere
it's in every direction and I think that
the the need is to try to think about it
all at once and to try to to develop the
possibility to see and to feel and to
sense and to to recognize that
complexity in every moment mm-hmm
interesting
so in other words don't get stuck in one
area of the problem or just just always
to be kind of not not to lose sight of
the did the global the total the overall
context is that what you're saying yeah
keep turning it how does this look from
my food perspective how does this look
from my kids perspective how does this
look from the perspective of people in
other countries how does this look from
the perspective of people in other
economic positions how does this look
from the perspective of my education
like what what good is my work now
what's essential hmm yeah what do I
actually have to offer now because I
think a lot of people are gonna come out
the other side of this realizing that so
much of what they have been able to give
really need it anymore
hmm and other people might find that
something essential that they had
forgotten or exactly uh-huh I know like
I was thinking about my own music right
and I for I've been playing music for a
long time and and I kind of let it slide
over the past few years just because
I've had a family and I've been working
very hard and and I've been doing
podcasts and writing and and all these
other things and somehow somehow I've
come back to music during the past three
weeks I think that's kind of interesting
I think of other people who might be
finding something that they had they had
neglected in their lives and discovering
how necessary and important that is for
them I have found that absolutely and I
think I think a lot of people are
finding that suddenly we're doing very
different things with our time but I
also have to say that I have people who
are close to me who have been intubated
and who have actually been through this
and people who are you know doctors and
scientists and things on the front line
trying to work this out
mmm find new ways through and the
experience of the comfortable people at
home who are having a little existential
quandary can really come off as well
maybe it's responsible of me to say that
and not say oh yes but my my neighbor
had a stroke and it's she's 80 years old
and she's afraid and she can't see her
grandchildren and you know I have to say
that side - I can't just talk about I I
mean I think if there's gonna be an
existential question it needs to include
the hard stuff certainly and that um the
recognition that you and I are healthy
today we can have this
conversation mm-hmm and there's it's not
like this virus is going to go back away
somewhere we're going to forever be
living in a world that this virus is in
we don't have it right now yeah but we
might have it next year and how will the
world have learned to respond to this
virus differently by next year what can
be what questions can be opened what
perspectives can be released what
imaginations can be delved into that
might make it so that in the future
there's another set of medical
procedures another set of cultural
responses another set of even you know
even existential philosophical
intellectual creative emotional
responses yeah well just the meditation
on death is in the forefront and I think
traditional cultures probably had more
of a direct contact with that and now
everybody's sort of thinking about it
all the time and thinking of their own
possible death you know that that again
that
those two ways that people people go
into fear or or people go into a deeper
reflection and start looking as you say
at the details of things and I don't
know of any sci-fi books that actually
described this situation - you know it's
not I don't I haven't read them all like
I haven't read all the philip k dick
books or I'm not a huge sci-fi guy but
no yeah well that again reality is
always stranger than fiction isn't it
exactly mm-hmm
that's the issue yeah that's really the
point Andrew mm-hmm
but this has been really fun yeah it's
been it's been marvelous Nora thank you
so much for taking the time thank you
for inviting me it's been a really rich
conversation for me and I hope I hope
it's a benefit to to other people and
other people can get a taste of your
complex and interesting oh gosh well
it's been really great to be in
conversation with you too and to poke
around at all this stuff I mean you know
there's there's no definitive knowing
now there's only inquiry mmm poking
around is a good word that's exactly
what we've been doing isn't it yeah
great yeah okay well maybe we can do it
again sometime
I would look forward to that okay thank
you so much and have a great day you too